All right, last talk of the the day and
then hopefully some fruit and some
drinks. It's getting hot in here. Um,
today we're going to talk about the
more of patterns and principles.
Probably not yet principles, but it's
been mentioned a few times. Our job is
changing. How is it changing? What's
affecting us? And um what I was trying
to wrap my head around uh in the
beginning of the year. This talk has
evolved through many iterations as kind
of technology has emerged but the
patterns pretty much stay the same. Just
the implementations are becoming more
actual and you can start seeing them in
the tools.
Um just want to mention this up front.
Um we I started uh this kind of website
for those who know the CNCF
landscape. Uh this is for AI developer
tools. We started with roughly 200 tools
maybe in January. We're closer to 500
tools right now. So it's uh it's my
daily job to kind of keep this also up
to date and whatever I come across as
tool I put there. So you don't have to
track the whole ecosystem and all the
social media for all the tools. So just
uh for you to have uh your daily fix of
the items.
Uh who am I for those who don't know me?
Um kind of the most people know me
around my work around DevOps and the
DevOps handbook if that rings about bell
for some people. moved into Dev Sec Ops
and then pretty much get bored about it
because it was like 10 15 years the same
CI/CD just with different words in a way
which is still cool but I kind of am a
person who likes to learn new things and
it kind of surfaces surfs on a little
bit of the chaotic early period and
trying to make sense of these things. I
did that with cloud. I did that with
mobile. I did that with serverless and
now it is AI and that is what excites me
actually. I curate content at the
community AI natively dev community.
That's also why we're here at the
meetup. Um and because where I travel I
try to tag on a meetup and that's how I
kind of get to know people who are also
interested in this thing.
So for those who remember cloud native
um again I was there in the beginning
and it felt like oh we're just going to
do the same but now in the cloud it
changed like microservices we we wrapped
our heads around like vans were no more
a thing access management need to be
different so the same thing is actually
happening with AI native and like the
reason for this slide is like a lot of
people just tag on and bolt on a little
bit of AI of what they're already doing.
I think it is you have to rethink your
workflow as you're currently doing this
with AI. So, it's good to get you
started to kind of get to know it, but
like it is fundamentally changing the
way we work and I'm trying to also kind
of highlight that in my session today.
I made this like beautiful diagram. It's
probably not the best diagram, but um
I'm not going to talk about code
generation. uh which might be surprise
to you because it's all actually been
mentioned in the two previous talks
generation is just happening faster
better more quality right and been
mentioned two times that review is
actually getting the bottleneck and the
human side the agent size bigger chunks
and so on so in the first thing I was
going to say is if AI writes the code
they're doing the dev right and we're
becoming the manager of those producing
the code. We're becoming the manager of
the agents doing this part of the review
that we already mentioned.
So if I review code,
I'm actually color blind. So red green
myths are really hard for me. Uh there
are different ways I can have a very
elaborous chat telling me about my code
which I don't have the stomach to read
everything it tells me right
maybe we can do it a little bit
different right if it just like
synthesizes certain changes with a
comment I get instant context so you see
it reduces the cognitive load of me
reviewing which is even though we are
still in the loop as the humans kind of
actually helps me to do this this is
nothing to do with code generation. This
is just helping me kind of do better and
faster code reviews. Right now,
why does it have to be a diff? I can
probably see on a diagram immediately if
I'm doing infrastructure as code what is
wrong and not wired up. I do not need to
see a diff of the code. Just to make you
thinking if I see that diagram,
sometimes it's easier to do a review.
Okay, Google had this thing notebook
LLM. you remember? So they built a
podcast generation of code divs into
their jewels at uh kind of codegen
though. Maybe if you know you can your
agents are coding all night and you
listen to the five minute snippet
episode in the morning that's what
they're aiming for. Anyway, just an
idea. It's reviewing reviewing and
people are experimenting with different
ways of reviewing stuff.
This brings me to a concept called the
moldable development environment. So
we're all known in your IDE that is very
text centric, very code centric. But as
we're spending less time in there, maybe
they have to be more get better at code
reviewing stuff, right? And the code
reviewing could be either some graphics,
some code, but it could also adapt
itself to the task at hand. maybe the
domain specific I'm doing a changing my
data model I'm doing changing UI so what
if actually the review system adapts
itself to me doing a review so this is
mostly concept there's a whole thing
called the glamorous toolkit or you are
happy to try this but the concept of
moldable development environment that
molds itself to what is the task at hand
is actually also a moldable exception
environment that helps you review
exceptions. So the same pattern applies
because you're ultimately responsible
for when the agents go wrong. Also,
now
we talk a lot about V coding in this
community, right? But it's rarely talked
on as a way to do review of an app. So
this was a, you know, a kind of golden
nugget for me. It asked the agent, can
you prove me that this is actually
working? And the agent builds a whole
fivecoded app to prove me and to do a
better job at reviewing, right? So we
can apply five coding on that as well
with UI components with domain specific
things to help help us there as well and
we come just a better review of that.
Now sometimes tools are trying to auto
commit so you don't have to review it,
right? If they're feeling certain enough
and so they flip the table by saying
let's do a commit and you can revert if
you don't like it instead of you having
to say yes all the time. Right? So it's
a different mentality of doing this.
But to do this we started seeing the
concept of checkpoints. you can roll
back up until a certain point in your
chat in your chat invocation in your
approval. So instead of it going off for
a long period and then saying I didn't
like it and then it goes off again, you
kind of go on the different steps and
say I didn't like it up until here and
now you can go. So checkpoints are
fundamental in a safe reviewing system
uh there as well.
And uh for those who hate the cloud
system, right? Uh access management
control on AWS is one of those most
complex things that you don't want to
touch is happening in our browser. We
have to say what our agents are allowed
to do. And yes, I know there's mode and
we say we do whatever or run it in a
container, but still we certainly not
want the agent to uh change. So we have
to do almost like user identity access
management for the agents there as well.
So becoming more complex. So I'm not
just a reviewer. I'm managing the whole
system. Who gets access? What is it
doing? Am I okay? Yes. No. And then on
top of that I have to worry about costs.
I mentioned in the first talk of Thomas
don't don't care about costs. Yeah.
Until you get your first bill. It's a
little bit like AWS. Yes. Don't worry
about it until you got that one system
that goes up and down. So I'm not saying
you have to worry about it but there's a
certain awareness like with it with
cloud native it's like fin how much are
you consuming and maybe you can give it
to a cheaper model uh that costs less
delegate this so I get it for reduction
you'd say just use as much as you want
because that's the typical trick but
then kind of it sets in what is actually
costing these things and are we using it
efficiently for the models that we
actually want funding enough um kind of
we saw the emergence of those max
licenses use it to the max unlimited use
right until they figure out like oh
there's actually people using this
unlimited so we have to put a limit on
these things because people are changing
this funny story somebody who optimized
their sleep because now they can code
for what is like the checkpoint of four
hours and then they kind of have a kind
of period they can't code and then they
go back again. I know funny I can do it
but the CL life is changing no matter
what we do and so that kind of like
upfront conventional coding think hard
what we want have the discussions and
then get into the zone and code not
happy anymore. It's like oh you want
need my attention need an answer need an
answer. It's almost like micromanaging
your agents as a boss, right? And we
don't want to do that, but it's maybe
the best we got until we get better
reviewing systems and things that help
us actually with the reading.
And congratulations,
you are now all ops. This is what it
feels uh if you were ops before DevOps.
people throwing code over the wall,
giving things you've never seen, you've
never written, and you are responsible
for running them, right? So,
congratulations. We're back. Yes.
Okay. So, this was you became a manager.
Congratulations.
But, um, we haven't actually discussed
what you want to build and how you want
to build this, right? So that's
typically the role of the QA kind of the
architect that says oh this is what
we're going to build this is how we're
going to build this all the requirements
and stuff. So that is also changing.
A very very lightweight thing is you
putting some of that knowledge of how
you want things built into a cursor
rules or you name it whatever flavor
dour you have about kind of specifying
the things you want. This was a very
simplistic early phase phase of this.
Now we're seeing a standardization. It's
not anymore. Well, it is still cloud MD,
but there's now an agent MD, Gemini MD,
and all those things. They're starting
to standardize that piece, which is
great because tools can now reuse that.
Same thing, we have now tools that
convert things from cursor rules to
rules and kind of, you know, but it's
similar to the S3 bucket that became
standard. So we're seeing a few of the
standards emerge just by the first kind
of adopter of a certain tool which is
great but we're specifying actually what
we want. This is not the review. This is
specifying what we want.
And so we're getting towards uh somebody
called it um we had you know prompt
engineering then we had context
engineering and then we had intent
engineering. We specify what we want and
the machines will take care of the
implementation given that we've given
them the guidelines how we want them to
build this and what we want him to build
this and go from there. It was a very
early on GitHub research. So it's not
anymore like yes we still have the code
text in the chat but you're specifying
what we want a plan is made and the code
is being generated. So that's where we
have him in the IDE
and Kira was probably the first IDE to
make this very explicit into the IDE.
Curo for those who don't know it's a
like an ID that was built by AWS outside
their Amazon Q system but
really make the difference between UI
code today or do you want to do the
specification proof approach right and
how does a specification look like? they
use the ears pattern but there's other
formats uh think of this mostly as BDD
type style descriptions
uh with examples and fix so it is
becoming more and more as a standard
thing you have as a spec kit still
experimental but again another company
supporting the idea of specifications as
such
this company I help uh Tesla they have a
concept called usage specs. So what they
do is they convert open source packages
to actually uh documentation. So when
you use the library in your code, you
can import those specifications on how
to use that. So it's a usage spec. It's
not how I want something to build, but
it's almost like documentation optimized
for an agent to be used.
So what can you put in spec? What we
want to build? How we want to build
this? design how we're building this. So
the whole workflow flow first do this
then do that then do that and then the
rules the pro the snippets and we can
even ask the agent to update the files
and how we do things was already
expressed a little bit like the
knowledge about that process and write
that as well. I often use the thing that
I code and then I say please write
everything that I get into a
specification that I can reuse. So it's
almost like saving the memory of
something that you've been working on
and then I start from there doing
further coding there as well.
And there's a flip side to this is it's
not only about your specification to
code. is also legacy code to
specification
because once I have the specification I
can just change it to let's rewrite this
Java lo and behold system to Rust and I
I just change that right probably not
going to work that perfectly but you
understand the idea
and the idea of the specification is
that it actually aligns
agents with humans we tell them what to
do, right? But for those that have been
around long enough and understands still
UML and kind of those things,
documentation and writing things down
actually also aligns humans together.
No, I didn't mean this. Oh, let's change
this because if it's not clear to you,
it might not be clear to the agent,
right? So, that is helping us in several
ways. Um funny thing this is that like
specifications are again on the rise
where we believe that writing everything
perfectly is going to help us. Uh guess
what like specifications are also
political.
I know I wrote this but actually I'm
going to do something different. That
actually I'm going to do something
different doesn't exist anymore with
agents. So it's going to be a fun thing
how we're going to handle those politics
with specifications.
Now the specifications grow you know
kind of security
QA like performance.
So we'll have to break them down. We
cannot just say I desire coding all
these things save this to a
specification and then say here's a
specification just go at it. People
learn that if it gets longer, you have
to break it down in smaller tasks. A
little bit like humans, you don't say
implement this feature of 100 different
things. You break them down. And that's
a challenge that we're now facing. How
do you actually break them down? How do
you make sure that the tasks are not
overlapping, actually not dependent on
each other? And that was also mentioned
by Robert kind of that dependency tree
is like a very challenging to kind of
break this down automatically through
planning
and then they just become part of our
canvan board. And so what we do is we
just watch the agents say act agent
please code this done right. So we see
them kind of progressing and working
together.
So
this kind of made us is we care less
about the specific implementation.
We kind of worry about actually the
intent was described. So that's where we
kind of move from
kind of low-level developer to becoming
more of an architect and how we tell
things to the agents. So let's go one
step back because how do we actually
know what we need to build? We think
it's a good idea, but maybe we should
ask the users. Maybe we should think
about what is the the feature that
actually going to bring value. So I
think this is definitely where V coding
shines. Product owner in the past had to
awesome developer who said like ah I
don't have time like put it somewhere in
the backlog. wait for me to do something
and they couldn't like see it. Now you
could say once the developer was free
then they could code on this but you
forgot that part of this is very
iteratively
I see it. Oh it's actually not what we
needed. It doesn't really feel good. So
there's like a very throwaway thing of
experimentation to figure out actually
what the user is you want the you the
the
feature is you want right so that
discovery process is where the v coding
charts you say oh no it's actually not
what oh I didn't think about this and
that is great for that
and why stop at generating one thing and
working on one thing why not have
multiple solutions
This is a very simplistic thing of
saying hey I want three versions of the
website three designs and I'll pick the
best one. Uh I'll implement me three
versions of this algorithm and I'll see
which one is best. So the choice is
changing the alternative of only having
to see one solution. So v coding is
still a bit linear but the fact that you
can spin up multiple things makes it
also very powerful. And there's two
reasons why you can do the parallelism.
Either we've already discussed doing
tasks at the same time, right? Breaking
down the task and then kind of saying,
"Oh, now now you can do this in parallel
or doing multiple kind of variations of
the same task and then selecting that.
Both valid, both helpful uh in selecting
what the right thing is that we have to
specify our intent."
We've seen kind of an approach kind of
doing some directories version one two
three 48. This is another way using git
work trees to kind of paralyze some of
your code uh working on different uh
directories uh on your laptop but still
doing it in a g in separate git trees.
Um you start seeing that the agents
actually start snapshotting and
committing things locally for the roll
back. So we're having a version system
before the version system. We're not
using the get one, but we have like a a
one that is before and some people use
gh for that because it's it's very
lightweight to do commits and then they
merge the branches there as well.
You can do it on your laptop being
mentioned that you can do it in the
cloud, you can do it in the container.
So kind of the the uh the founders of
Docker are also now uh into a company
called Dagger. They allow you to spin up
multiple coding agents within
containers. So here's the example of
just saying it hooks into your MCP by
saying I want two variations. It spins
up two kind of containers and kind of
one uh is from there.
So I've show uh I hope I made you see
that it's we worry less about the
delivery but more about the discovery.
what is the right thing that we need to
build instead of it's still like okay
this is the only thing we can build the
only thing where we have money for let's
build that and keep that disabled under
control
and then the last piece is converting
everything we learned in that whole
cycle to knowledge that's already been
mentioned as well now what are other
sources of knowledge documentation right
a company called context 7 kind of made
a very great interface uh of you able to
use the most up-to-date documentation
when you generate code because the LLMs
have been trained on all versions right
helps uh getting there as knowledge I
can also turn my codebase into lessons
new engineer comes in and says I want to
learn about the codebase right okay
here's a bunch of lessons generated with
the eye or a person leaves right there's
no drain because the AI will help them
understand and keep them up to with the
knowledge
and it's been interesting that even
cloud code is tipping and tapping into
that learning aspect. So cloud code also
has a learning mode you exploring things
about your code asking things about your
codebase. It's not just about your code
generation right now.
And then it could be as simple as you
know the first kind of very very early
science for this was somebody keeping an
almost like a a log of everything they
did. This was the memory. First we did
that feature then we did this and this
is how we applied it almost like the
change lock the first thing. So you
don't reimplement the same feature again
next year right just keep that track of
that knowledge as well.
And I find this interesting. Um, it's
it's a little bit hard to see, but um,
this was a screenshot of Devon while you
were coding. It says, "Oh, this looks
like important. This looks like
knowledge. Should we save this?" Right?
This was probably the first. Now, in
qual code, for example, you can do the
what's it? The the hash sign to save
something into the memory also
knowledge. So you see kind of like
inline knowledge discovery and saving is
something that will creep more into the
tools as well
and then reusing it across as we
mentioned before uh not only one agent
even across tools uh putting it into a
file that's been mentioned putting it
into a memory database putting into a
knowledge uh database uh having an
orchestrator agent say this is what
actually should go
Um, and then we start going into even
more uncharted territory is let's spin
up like a bunch of cloud systems like a
swarm. Um, I often refer to this almost
like the the mo programming versions of
our coding agents spin things up. They
have a bunch of rules. Each of them have
a different role and then they come back
uh in the evening and they run.
I find it an interesting experiment and
it probably will kind of uh you know if
you specify things you will get good
results but the longer these things run
the harder it is to review because it
becomes that big for you and doing the
review and then we're back actually to
pattern number one how to deal with
better reviews.
Um
and then you can use that knowledge not
just for the code generation but if
somebody has a question on the agent on
your PR on your decision making all the
knowledge is there as well. So that's it
those were the four patterns. Um I hope
you they make sense to you. Uh I the
last thing I want to highlight is that
if you're a senior developer, you're
likely
have been moving to this side because
you care about the actually running the
system. You've been care about queuing
the architecting the system. If you're
more senior, you've been getting closer
to the business because you actually
wanted to know what was the best thing
you should be building and then you
start documenting things for people
around you there as well. So actually
the whole thing drives us to be even
more senior and helps us with tools to
kind of uh go better in our journey as a
developer as well.
this uh it's probably for my new deck
but you can see there's an emerging new
flow where we're managing the intent
gets broken down into a plan mode
something in parallel gets done and then
the review is still where we say yes no
and then all across the whole thing
we're saving the knowledge but all this
is actually you can think of this as a
CI/CD flow
but it's happening on the developer
laptop
and then it now gets purged and so
that's why I think that um
once this new pattern starts changing
and people are adopting this the whole
CI/Crally
will likely change as well because it
feels a little bit redundant right like
we're merging here locally and then
we're doing it back again but everybody
body is doing this locally. So I I have
no clue where this kind of is going
directionally. But I I think for those
saying like, oh, we're putting AI in our
DevOps and our CI/CD workflow. I think
this first has to settle and then kind
of we'll see how that one will change
the result.
Last thing, we're doing the meetups
here. AI native meetup. Um we also have
a conference coming up. I know it's in
New York but there might be some
international people or people willing
to travel and also uh live stream uh
most of it there's a CFP you can help
people to travel that's useful and so
you see it's centered around
specifications generating the code doing
a review learning knowledge and getting
stories out like tonight uh I hope you
enjoyed uh the session tonight and if so
uh you can find way more of these talks
uh on our YouTube channel, on our
podcast, um on our website. Uh and we're
trying to get the stories out and uh
it's great that you were willing to
listen and also to the speakers and the
organizers to help us find uh the people
to do. Thank you very much.
[Applause]
any questions?
[Music]
>> Thanks, Patrick. And I I encourage
everyone to watch your talks because
it's fun to see the evolvement of them.
Uh how you keep changing the slides and
new ideas. Um, so the spec part, um, I'm
I'm I'm I'm really trying myself to
write these specs and and have them.
What I'm not really good at yet is or
I'm still trying to struggling with is
like at the end of the day, I mean, uh,
code is is where the truth is, right?
Um, so do you have some and and for for
me it's it's still very sequential
waterfall. I write the specs, then I'm
generating something and then the
markdowns lie there and sometimes the
agent picks it up and sometimes it
doesn't. Do you have some some insights,
experience, thoughts of how like code
and and specs continuously update
themselves kind of like in in a
continuous way.
>> Yeah. What you start seeing is that um
where we initially started with
specifications as we were writing
documentation
uh you start seeing
um the increase of using examples
uh in there. So it's almost like u
executable code. I know it's pseudo
code, but at least there's a way of kind
of uh referring to this piece that I
described should be covered in this
test. And so one of the um like like in
the BDD uh of Kira and others, you can
specify those examples. Now I agree that
it's tricky if the eye writes, you know,
kind of code and it AI writes the tests,
but that is a
challenge but you can force this uh in a
way model maybe with multiple agents. So
that's what people have been trying to
kind of like uh keep it under control.
But the but the main answer to your
question is find a way to relate the
piece of specification to executable
tests and then have that generate so at
least you have some link. Uh that's the
best I've seen so far. Yeah, I'm I've
I'm I'm trying this with Playright tests
and it fails me big time because they're
so flaky and they break all the time. So
I'm not not not good at that at all yet.
>> Yeah. Well, play even without AI it was
flaky. Uh that that's just a matter
that's because of the selectors and all
that way is very clunky. But what I was
referring to is even just the the basic
TDD and BDD tests which in general
you'll you'll have a better result and
then go into a browser uh as such.
>> Yeah, for some reason I've never thought
about BDD until tonight. I'll I'll try
this.
>> Okay, cool. Thanks. Thanks.
Maybe I misunderstood a little bit but
you're saying that CICD will evolve and
uh in some part of why I agree with you
but I think and it's you made the M
during your speech about the reviewing
and reviewing it's a huge part of the
CIC. So of course you have the unit
testings and static analysis and
everything which run into the CI/CD but
the the way I see it is that uh it will
be even growing the CI/CD to help with
the viewing process because most of the
work which was done before in NAV will
get basically done at the review process
and the review process is basically will
be the step of the CIC.
>> So, uh I don't think I contradicted you.
It's probably something you heard in
this. I'm not saying the CI/CD loop is
going away the central one, but I think
it will be evolving in a way that it
maybe learn from feedback that the
agents already did like internally uh
and automatically. So, it isn't kind of
we throw everything, we trust nobody and
then we do this CI/CD system again over
there. uh think of this almost like
having
12 or you know 30 different feature
branches being tested by different
people and different tools and in that
way now most of the CI/CD is kind of
okay at the central pipeline where
everything's getting so I I will see
like a parallelism there happening as
well um I agree with you that you you
cannot put this like straight to code
that's why in the I emphasize the review
system. But uh when people say, "Oh, I'm
putting AI in my C ICD loop." Um I think
it's helpful for some quality and more
ML ops or AI ops that you're doing
there. But I think interfacing
with the multitude of agents doing
reviews, doing changes. uh the question
comes is um how much risk how much
review uh do you want to do uh in these
pieces uh as well but that brings up the
piece of test coverage again so um and I
I hope I don't know where it's heading
but I I feel this needs to change first
before we actually can see the impact on
the sentenc systems
>> and my second question is basically code
was a way for humans to understand more
than machine what needs to be done
because in the end machine are fine with
my code and the shadow is the work we
have in the languages with AI generating
more and more code and doing basically
the heavy lifting do we still need in
the end uh
intermediate programming language
>> why not have AI just I I know it's not
ready yet, but write directly write by
code and uh use other means to check
that we're happy with that even if we
don't ourself understand the
intermediate code or the whatever code
it's generating.
Yeah, it's it's something that comes up
quite a bit like say kind of a low level
and we're moving up the abstraction. We
don't need to see this anymore. Um
I think as we moved into the cloud you
also had more and more abstraction. You
actually need to see what the disk is
doing underneath. You actually need to
see what kind of you know the network uh
is doing. um when it fails we want to
all right that's my answer right but not
everybody will have to look at the
failure but it could be and that's why I
mentioned the multiple exceptions if it
adapts the UI in a way that I can
understand what is failing and I don't
have to see the intermediate code that's
great now I'm not
I'm not in a camp that says the code
being generated if If you throw enough
money and kind of resources at it, it
will be perfect. I am still somewhere an
ops person that says I do not trust this
and there's no proof or no way that we
can be certain about it not
hallucinating and doing bad things. Now
we can throw a lot more tools to it like
static analysis and we can do it in Rust
and kind of create some uh you know
better and kind of system but do I
fundamentally trust it to go live
without having to look at it? That
brings up the question is I would do
that if the risk is okay but I don't
know what that risk okay means to you
right so if something went wrong and
that's the story of the intern pushing
something to the codebase uh and then
pushing that to production if I have a
test harness that stops it I'm fine with
going there or if I can contain one
change to two users and they have low
impact then it's okay as well. So kind
of that brings the discussion to what
risk are you willing to take to what
kind of systems do you want AI to touch?
But I don't see
any I haven't seen any hints by people
saying
we trust this piece enough by going
directly into prod. I've been looking
really hard because definitely I want to
have that DevOps connection that like we
we kind of went through to production.
Yes, there's people taking risks and say
it's fine. This is something that can
crash, but do I actually want that to
happen? Um,
you could say we had done automation
before, right? CI/CD and instead of one
system, we brought up a 100 systems, but
that was predictable in a certain way.
This one, I don't know. I I still feel
uneasy about this in that term, but I
guess we probably move somewhere
to food and beer or something.
>> Thank you.
[Applause]